Finding Aid for the Davida Rochlin Papers LSC.2369
UCLA Library Special Collections
Davida Rochlin papers
1971-2019
UCLA Library Special Collections
Rochlin, Davida
LSC.2369
42 linear feet (26 boxes, 6 flat boxes, 4 telescope boxes, 1 shoebox, and 12 map folders)
333 born-digital carriers (311 unprocessed 3.5 inch floppy disks, 2 unprocessed 5.25 inch floppy disks, 20 unprocessed CDs)
Davida Rochlin is a second-generation Los Angeles architect born in October 1951. Rochlin received her Bachelor of Arts and Master's in Architecture from the University of California, Berkeley in 1973 and 1976, respectively. Rochlin gained notoriety early on in her career with research begun under the mentorship of American architect Joseph Esherick for her master's thesis on the American porch. This research on the porch has shaped Rochlin's work throughout her career, which focuses on sustainable design, ranges from residential architecture to medical and educational buildings, and encompasses exhibitions and research. The collection contains student work and records produced by Rochlin while enrolled as an architecture student in the School of Environmental Design at UC Berkeley and early career works, including apprenticeships for various architectural firms and freelance jobs. Also included are materials relating to Rochlin's professional work about the American porch, such as research, preparation for the 1983-84 exhibition The Front Porch at the Craft and Folk Art Museum (CAFAM), published magazine articles, book proposals, and exhibition materials from Rochlin's 2010 exhibition The New American Porch shown at the LA Archive Gallery. Materials created by Davida Rochlin Architecture (DRAIA), Rochlin's architecture firm, include drawings, architectural plans, research, photographs, correspondence, and other office records.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL/AUDIO MATERIALS: Digital/audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Davida Rochlin and Fred J. Marcus, 2018.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9990105133606533
Biographical / Historical
Davida Rochlin is a second-generation Los Angeles architect. She was born in October 1951 to writer and historian Harriet Rochlin and architect-turned-performer and writer Fred Rochlin. She received her Bachelor of Arts in Architecture from the University of California, Berkeley (cum laude) in 1973. She went on to earn a master's degree in Architecture, also from UC Berkeley, in 1976. Rochlin gained notoriety early on in her career with research begun while working on her master's thesis on the American porch, under the mentorship of American architect Joseph Esherick. This research on the porch has shaped Rochlin's work throughout her career.
After earning her MA, Rochlin began her career at Esherick, Homsey, Dodge and Davis in San Francisco. Next, she worked briefly for Miller, Waltz and Diedrich in Atlanta. She then went on to serve as Project Planner and Architect at Rochlin and Baran (later RBB Architects) until 1986. During this time she also continued research on the American porch in Atlanta and created The Front Porch exhibition at the Craft and Folk Art Museum (CAFAM), which was part of a regional symposium and series of exhibitions titled Home Sweet Home: American Domestic Vernacular Architecture.
In 1986 Rochlin opened her own firm, Davida Rochlin Architecture (DRAIA), which operated out of the landmark Barry Building in Brentwood, California for thirty years. As of 2019, DRAIA is still active and has relocated to Santa Monica. Rochlin is a member of the American Institute of Architects (AIA), United States Green Building Council, and the International Living Future Institute. Rochlin's work exhibits a specialization in American domestic vernacular architecture and sustainability. The porch, as both a cultural icon and a passive solar design solution, shapes the theory and design behind Rochlin's architecture, which focuses on energy efficiency and renewable energy. Rochlin's work both at other firms in the early stages of her career and under DRAIA is not limited to residential and includes medical, education, and office buildings.
Some of Davida Rochlin's most well known works include the Market Street Residences (San Francisco, CA), Sea Level House (Malibu, CA), Honakai House (Big Island, HA), Rancho Girasol (Taos, NM), Elijah Wood Residence (Santa Monica, CA), Kenquest Corporate Headquarters (Beverly Hills, CA), and Leo Baeck Temple Religious School renovation (Los Angeles, CA).
Notable writing featuring DRAIA work can be found in publications including the New York Times, Los Angeles Times, Architecture, Metropolitan Home, Fine Homebuilding, LA Architect, Martha Stewart Living, artslant.com, and chanceofrain.com. Rochlin has also exhibited at the Craft and Folk Art Museum, Architecture and Design Museum, and LA Archive Gallery, all of which are located in Los Angeles.
Scope and Content
Collection contains student work and records produced by Davida Rochlin while enrolled as an architecture student in the School of Environmental Design at UC Berkeley and early career works. Included in early career works are materials from architectural apprenticeships for architectural firms and freelance jobs. Also included are materials relating to Rochlin's professional work around the American porch, such as research, exhibition preparation for The Front Porch exhibition at the Craft and Folk Art Museum, published magazine articles, book proposals, and materials from Rochlin's 2010 exhibition, The New American Porch. Materials created by Davida Rochlin Architecture include drawings, architectural plans, research, photographs, correspondence, and other office records.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Academic work, 1971-1982
Series 2: Early work, 1976-1986
Series 3: The American porch, 1976-1994
Subseries 3.1: Porch research, 1976-1984
Subseries 3.2: The Front Porch exhibition, 1981-1984
Subseries 3.3: Porch book and publications, 1983-1994
Series 4: Davida Rochlin Architecture (DRAIA) work, 1980-2019
Subseries 4.1: Davida Rochlin Architecture (DRAIA) projects, 1980-2010
Subseries 4.2: Thomas/Goff Residence (Honakai House), 2001-2004
Subseries 4.3: Elijah Wood Residence, 2000
Subseries 4.4: Sea Level House, 2003-2008
Subseries 4.5: Market Street Residences, 2014-2015
Series 5: Davida Rochlin Architecture (DRAIA) office records, 1984-2017
Subseries 5.1: General office records, 1984-2017
Subseries 5.2: Brochures and requests for proposals (RFPs), 1999-2010
Subseries 5.3: Press and publications, 1983-2017
Series 6: The New American Porch pop-up show, 2010
Series 7: Digital Materials, 1994-2010
The materials largely retain their existing order, since they came to UCLA pre-processed into series and subseries. Some subseries were combined for clarity. These series follow Rochlin's career in chronological order.
Architects -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives; Architecture -- California -- 20th century; Architecture, Domestic -- California, Southern; Rochlin, Davida -- Archives
- Series 1: Academic work, 1971-1982; 1971-1976
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains student work by and records of Davida Rochlin while enrolled as an architecture student in the School of Environmental Design at UC Berkeley. Included are official honors letters from the dean, transcripts, and diplomas. Also included are portfolios, slides, photographs, and drawings from academic work, including design studios, such as the Chair Design Studio and San Francisco Marshall Library design; Smyth-Fernwald Child Care Center independent study and field work; and Ramona's Café Remodel for a School of Environmental Design student competition. The series also contains research, notes, drafts, and a final copy of Rochlin's master's thesis on the American porch. Additional materials include photographs and slides of porches collected during Rochlin's time at UC Berkeley, particularly while working on the thesis.
  - Diplomas (BA and MA), 1973, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - UC Berkeley academic honors, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic records, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - UC Berkeley design studio portfolios, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Chair design project, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - San Francisco Marshall Library design studio project, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - An Economical Porch project, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Porch swing design project, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Porch poster project, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - School models, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Design studio work, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Plans for Architectural Field Office project and plans and photographs for Experimental School project for Architecture 101. Course description for Architecture 102B and plans for Coffeehouse project for that course. Plans and photographs for Architecture 102C Day Care Center project.
  - Design studio images, circa 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Images of Ramona's Cafe (Wurster Hall) from School of Environmental Design student competition, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Slides of projects at UC Berkeley, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Smyth-Fernwald news and flyers, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Publications, news, and flyers for events around the Smyth-Fernwald Child Care Center, where Rochlin worked as a student architect from November 1972-October 1973, as part of Architecture 102D and 197.
  - Smyth-Fernwald journal, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Smyth-Fernwald photographs, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Smyth-Fernwald analysis of architectural work, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Smyth-Fernwald plans, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - UC Berkeley photography coursework, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Porch research: quotes from literature, circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Porch research: quotes, circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Porch research: notes and images, circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Porch research: furniture, circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    One black-and-white photograph of a couple on a porch and one advertisement/price list for willow furniture from McGibbon & Co. New York.
  - Porch research: notes and inspiration, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Porch slideshow #1, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Porch negatives, circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Porch drawings, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Porch quotes ("Brainpicking peoples' comments on the porch"), circa 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The American Porch master's thesis drafts, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - The American Porch master's thesis copy, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - The American Porch master's thesis final, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Porch negatives, circa 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Slides of porches, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Slides (photographs) of porches dated 1975-1982. Copies of three transmittals for the following projects: Redbook—the American Porch (July 1984), Redbook—Porch Sampler (1984), and Porch Sampler (undated).
  - Slides of porches, 1975-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Slides of porches, 1975-1982 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Porch postcards, photographs, and slides, circa 1971-1976 (Box 5)
    This file includes photographs, drawings, and slides collected during Rochlin's time at UC Berkeley. These materials relate to her research on the American Porch and are divided by region, style, or genre.
- Series 2: Early work, 1976-1986
  This series contains work from Davida Rochlin's early career. It includes work completed during architectural apprenticeships for various architectural firms, as well as freelance assignments. The majority of the coverage is work done for the firm Rochlin and Baran, including the Redken Research Center Laboratory (circa 1978-1986), Kaiser West LA Clinic and Hospital (1982), Northridge Pediatrics (1983), Oak Hills Medical Office Building (circa 1978-1986), and Good Samaritan Medical Office Building (circa 1978-1986).
  Arrangement
  This work is organized chronologically, with the exception of the photographs of medical projects for Rochlin and Baran, which are housed separately.
  - Resumé, circa 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Architectural models for Miller, Waltz & Diedrich, Atlanta, GA, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Redken Research Center/Laboratory project for Rochlin & Baran, circa 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Redken Research Laboratory construction photographs, Rochlin & Baran, circa 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kaiser West LA Clinic addition for Rochlin & Baran, circa 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kaiser West LA Hospital, Rochlin & Baran, comprehensive plan, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Northridge Pediatrics before/after photographs for Rochlin & Baran, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Oak Hills Medical Office Building, Rochlin & Baran, circa 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Good Samaritan Medical Office Building, Rochlin & Baran, circa 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Invitation design for Nancy Silverton publication celebration, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of medical projects for Rochlin & Baran, 1982 (Box 5)
- Series 3: The American porch, 1976-1994; 1976-1986
  This series contains materials related to the American porch created during Rochlin's professional career. It includes research done in Atlanta and preparatory materials related The Front Porch exhibition at the Craft and Folk Art Museum in Los Angeles. Published magazine articles and book proposals on the American porch are also included.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO AND DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Subseries 3.1: Porch research, 1976-1984
    This subseries includes photographs, slides, notes, maps, and brochures collected during Rochlin's time conducting research in Atlanta, Georgia. Coverage includes research for the Ludlow Porch Show, research for an unpublished article on the Southern porch for Brown's Guide to Georgia, and Evolution of the Georgia Porch, written by Davida Rochlin and Andrea Niles for the Georgia Trust for Historic Preservation.
    - Slides of porches, 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Atlanta porch research: historic photographs, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ludlow Porch Show correspondence and excerpts, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Georgia Porch Magazine submission, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Research for Brown's Guide to Georgia, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Porch swing design research for Georgia Trust for Historic Preservation, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Atlanta porch photographs, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Mainly consists of photographs of porches and people from around Atlanta. Also includes a printout of images and information on the Menard home and the historic Jarrett Manor.
    - Maps and guidebooks of Georgia cities, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Collected notes, publications, and research done on the porch in Atlanta, GA, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Collected porch images from Atlanta, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Porch furniture negatives, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Porch definitions, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Examples of porches in art, 1978-1983 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Aspen, Colorado porch research, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Georgia porch photographs, circa 1976-1984 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 3.2: The Front Porch exhibition, 1981-1984
    This subseries contains research and preparatory materials for The Front Porch exhibition organized by Rochlin at the Craft and Folk Art Museum (CAFAM) in Los Angeles, California, which ran from October 1983 to January 1984. These materials include writing, correspondence, notes, drawings, floor plans, budget and proposal, photographs and slides, reviews, advertising, newspaper publications, drafts of the catalog essay, and a copy of the exhibition catalog, Home Sweet Home: American Domestic Vernacular Architecture.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    - Correspondence with Harriet Rochlin, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum show concept, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      An overview of "The Temple, the Cabin and the Barn" by Charles W. Moore.
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum contracts, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - American Domestic Vernacular Architecture proposal, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum guidelines, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Drawings, writings, and budget for exhibit, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum floor plan, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 7, Box 39)
    - Mock-ups for exhibit, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Show preparation, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Includes notes, images (with list of figures), drawings, and budget in preparation for the CAFAM exhibition.
    - Budget and proposal, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Exhibition construction photographs, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with the Craft & Folk Art Museum, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition materials and specifications, circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 13-15)
    - Exhibit programming, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Exhibit notes, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Theme photograph: dog with American flag, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition announcement, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Presentation notes, slide show #1, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Exhibit images, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Atlanta Historical Society photo order, 1978-1983 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Peanuts cartoon for exhibition, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Photograph orders, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Georgia Historical Society images, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Garrison Keillor article "Porch Song" for Ambassador Magazine, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Planning porch plants and notes, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Planning music for porch exhibition, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      This folder contains an audiocassette.
    - Fundraising, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Craft and Folk Art Museum (CAFAM) calendar, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Exhibition negatives and photographic transparencies, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Catalog essay drafts, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Publicity, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Drawings and notes, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Catalog essay, final copy, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 21)
      In addition to the final copy of the catalog essay, this folder includes some handwritten notes and bibliographical information.
    - Catalog essay research and criticism, circa 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum show time log, 1982-1983 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Home Sweet Home exhibition catalog and publicity, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - New York Times review, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper articles and publications, 1983, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      This folder contains photographic stills from a News 4 LA television broadcast and a September 1999 issue of Los Angeles Magazine with an article on Fred Rochlin, in addition to newspaper articles about the exhibition.
    - UCLA Extension advertisement, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Traveling opportunities, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Traveling information, circa 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Magazine announcing exhibition opening, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Sunset Magazine review, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Fine Homebuilding Magazine coverage and review, 1983-1984 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Craft & Folk Art Museum show exhibit photographic transparencies, circa 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Porch exhibit oversize photographs, circa 1982-1983 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3.3: Porch book and publications, 1983-1994
    The majority of this subseries contains correspondence with Angela Miller of the Miller Agency for a potential book about the American porch with drafts, writing, and proposals sent to publishers. Additional materials include photographs, magazines, slides, negatives, and a copy of the book Porches, Decks and Outbuildings, which contains Rochlin's American Porch essay.
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    - Porch book resume and proposals, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Collected porch images, notes, and quotations, 1979-1994 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
    - Fine Homebuilding Magazine article preparation, 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Seaside, Florida correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Old-House Journal porch issue, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Includes a copy of the magazine in addition to correspondence with the editor and copies of informational notes and images sent to the magazine.
    - Home Magazine day planner and address book, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Porch book proposal materials, circa 1992-1994 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
      Includes drafts and materials for a book proposal on the porch. Additional materials include a collection of newspaper and magazine articles dealing with the American porch from 1979, 1992, 1993, and 1994.
    - Collected research and writing on the porch, circa 1992-1994 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      A collection of newspaper and magazine articles and book excerpts on the porch collected by Rochlin. The majority of excerpts date from 1982-1994, with additional passages published in 1902, 1925, and 1927.
    - Correspondence with Redbook, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Redbook transmittals, 1984-1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - The Evolution of the Porch, circa 1983-1994 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Book proposal edited by Angela Miller, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Book proposal materials with the Miller Agency, 1991-1995 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Book proposal materials with the Miller Agency, 1988-1997 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Book proposal for Mark Magowen (Abbeville Press), 1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Book proposal for Peregrine Smith, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Book proposal for Abbeville Press, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Book proposal outline, 1991 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Book outline, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Sample book proposal from Sally F. Robbins, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - American Porches essay and outline, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Book research and contacts, circa 1983-1994 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Tim Street-Porter photography, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with the Preservation Press, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - New Shelter Magazine correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, notes, and research, 1983-1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Book proposal for Diane Maddex, 1991-1997 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Photographs and negatives of Georgia Porches, circa 1983-1994 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Digital porch book proposal, circa 1983-1994 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      This folder contains two 3.5 inch floppy disks.